It's breathtaking. And um
after he he died he died from what we
believe was probably prostate cancer.
>> Okay.
>> So
they realized he was near the end. And
so they put him on a donkey and the
donkey carried him all the way from the
north side of the island all the way to
the port down the mountain and they put
him on a boat and they sent him to
Athens to the Red Cross hospital which
is still there. It's right by the
American Embassy.
And he died a couple days later in the
hospital. Well, there was a man in the
next bed who was a farmer who had fallen
off a retaining wall and he broke his
back and was paralyzed from the neck
down. And he was crying in the bed, not
because he was paralyzed, but because
now he wouldn't be able to farm. And so
his wife and his children would starve.
And so
the saint died in the next bed. And when
the nuns went in to wash his body, they
took his sweater off and they put it on
the bed where the paralyzed man was and
he got up and walked.
>> Unbelievable.
>> It was the first of the I had chills. It
was the first of the major of the major
miracles that were attributed to him.
As soon as these miracles began
happening, it was before he was even
buried,
the patriarch
of Alexandria
said, "Oh my god, I made a terrible
mistake."
Or, "We made a terrible mistake." And
they issued an apology
and said that they were wrong. He was
right. But remember all those years,
>> I mean, we're talking 25 30
>> longer than that, 40
>> 40 years,
>> 45 years, he forgave all of them. He he
still tried to to reclaim his
reputation, but he forgave all of them.
So, I'm reading this. The the the bishop
of Pittsburgh was a big fan of mine, the
Greek Orthodox bishop of Pittsburgh, and
he would come to prison to visit me, and
he brought me that book. So, I read the
book. I was like, "This is incredible."
And then you couple that with, you know,
Nelson Mandela's ability to forgive or
or Martin Luther King's ability to
forgive and Necarios's ability to
forgive. And I thought to myself, and
who am I that I should hold a grudge? I
mean, these men were wronged so much
worse than I was.
My God, if they can forgive, I certainly
can.
I'm friends now with a man named
Muhammadu Slahi. Has anybody ever heard
of him? Muhammadu Slahi.
This is a story.
Muhammad Uslahi was a Moritanian
medical student in Germany,
not a political bone in his body.
And he's just living his best life going
to med school. He's going to be a
doctor. He wants to go back to Moretania
one day because it's poor and he wants
to help his people etc etc. He's got a
cousin in Beirut. Okay. And the cousin's
brother is in Noakshhat orania getting
married.
So the cousin in Beirut calls Muhammadu
and says, "Hey, my brother's getting
married in Noakhat. Are you going to go
to the wedding?" And he says, "Yeah, I'm
going to go to the wedding. Are you
going to go to the wedding?" He said,
"No, I can't. I can't leave Beirut. He
couldn't leave Beirut because he was in
al-Qaeda. Muhammad who didn't know his
cousin's in al-Qaeda.
CIA did.
And they said, "Hey, hey, hey, this
al-Qaeda guy in Beirut, he's calling
this guy in Germany, and the guy in
Germany is going to go to Noakchot. We
better call the Moritanians and snatch
this guy."
So Muhammadu flies back to Noakshot,
goes to his cousin's wedding. The cops
come in, they say, "You, some people
outside want to see you." We put a bag
on his head, we put him in a jeep, take
him to the airport, and fly him to
Guantanamo.
He has no idea what is happening to him.
And we tortured him for 14 years.
And after 14 years, we said, "You know
what? this guy actually doesn't know
anything.
Maybe he really was just a medical
student.
And we let him go.
So, he got out.
>> Now, when he gets out, he's what, 36?
>> Oh, yeah. He's in his late 30s. He gets
out like the week that I get out of
prison. And he immediately sets up a
Twitter account. So, I'm on Twitter and
I see Muhammad Slah. I remember when we
snatched him because there were a bunch
of us saying, "Wait a minute, wait a
minute. We don't have any evidence
against this guy at all. Just because he
had one phone call with with some random
low-level al-Qaeda nobody in Beirut,
we're going to snatch the guy."
I was always overruled in those
conversations. There were half a dozen
people like that that we ended up
concluding, it was the wrong guy. What
are you going to do? So I tweeted at him
and I said, "Muhammadu,
my my government will never apologize
for what it did to you, so I apologize
for what it did to you." And he
immediately DMs me and we've been
friends ever since. I wrote the forward
to his book and he uh is the guest
lecturer in every one of my classes on
the history of terrorism. I I teach a
grad school course at the University of
Salamanca in Spain.
And um I said to him, you know, you are
like Nelson Mandela and Martin Luther
King and a man you've probably never
heard of, St. Nectario. I said, your
ability to forgive transcends anything
that I've ever seen in anybody before.
And he said, "What am I going to do? I
was going to be a doctor. They took it
away from me. What am I just going to,
you know, say, oh, woe is me. I was
supposed to be a doctor." He said, "I
have to just get on with my life."
So now, of all things, he he lives in
the Netherlands.
He got married. He has two kids. And he
teaches elementary school art
and started a new life and is happy and
prosperous because he was able to
forgive.
And I have nothing but the deepest
admiration for something like that. So
if you didn't have your faith,
>> I would have nothing.
>> You'd be crushed.
>> So I want to I want to go to this. So
you it's it's hard to say this to you,
but you're really blessed because most
people there are a lot of people there's
a wonderful movie by Terrence Malik, a
hidden life on Fran Jaggert. Um Fran
Jaggert was an Austrian farmer who
refused to say the loyalty oath to
Hitler. His bishop said, "Be prudent to
just say it."
>> His priest said, "You're being
ridiculous. Just say the loyalty oath."
>> He said, "I'm never going to say it. I'm
a Catholic man.
>> They tortured him. The SS officer was
Catholic and sat him down and said, "Do
you think that the world's going to
celebrate you? They'll never know what
you do. This this is your, you know,
they'll never see what you're doing.
You're not a hero. No one will know. No
one will care." And that is actually
true. Most people who make the decisions
that Fran Jagger, your friend Muhammad,
you made, they're not redeemed in this
life.
>> No.
>> And the world never knows. So this is my
question to you.
I want you to maybe tell us about the
darkest years of this experience. And if
during those darkest years, did you
resent the decision you made? Did you
regret the decision you made? And if you
knew there would never be a redemption
in this life,
uh would it have been worth it? That's
the hardest question.
I can tell you
my the two hardest times of my life.
The night of my arrest, never saw it
coming. And it had been in the works for
years. I never ever saw it coming. And
the night I was arrested, they released
me and um it was about 10 o'clock and my
wife said, "Come on, let's go to bed.
It's been a heck of a day." And I said,
"No, I'm going to stay up and watch TV."
I wasn't going to stay up and watch TV.
I was going to go down to the garage and
start the car and lay on the back seat
and just let it finish me. And I think
she suspected
and she said, "No, come on upstairs."
And I said, "No, I'm not ready." She
said, "I'm insisting."
And so I did. that I went upstairs
and um and then my brother called me the
next day and he said, "I know you can't
see this, but this is going to turn out
to be the best thing that ever happened
to you." And I said, "No, I can't see
it. I appreciate you saying it, but no,
this is the worst thing that ever
happened to me." But then I decided to
fight. And my my ex-wife now, she said
she was trying to buck me up and she
said, "They have consistently
underestimated your resolve. They've
consistently underestimated your
toughness. You have to fight them." And
then later she said,
"You have to keep talking about your
case because eventually they're going to
move on to their next target." Which
they did. It was Ed Snowden. And she
said, 'If you keep talking, your side of
the story will become the side of record
>> because you're not going to gaslight
forever.
>> That's right.
>> They move on always.
>> They move on. They always move on.
>> And she was right.
>> Wise woman.
>> Yeah.
>> In that instance. In that instance.
>> Yeah,
>> we'll give her that one.
>> I will admit to you that I am I am
prohibited by court order from
discussing my ex-wife in uh in detail.
>> Yeah. But I will say that um
I will say that June 30th, 2018,
three plus years after I got out of
prison was the worst day of my life.
>> Okay?
>> Because
well in Latin the words infle deleto
mean something. And um I thought going
to prison was bad. This was way way
worse than going to prison. But you
know, I remember laying there in bed,
quite literally laying in bed, I
suffered terribly from insomnia,
3:00 in the morning, and against the
advice of every intelligence officer
I've ever known, I have an Alexa in my
room, right? Because it plays SiriusXM
radio every morning. You know,
>> losing our privacy is worth free. It's
like exactly Alexa. We all make that
same decision.
>> Yeah. So I I'm laying there and I said,
"Alexa,
what percentage of marriages that begin
as affairs end in divorce?" And she
says, "The percentage of marriages that
begin as affairs and end in divorce is
93%." And I was like, "Oh, thank God."
Okay, so at least I've got that. I'm
going to hang on to that for a little
while. And then I'm laying there and I
have I have an econostasis in my room,
right?
icons that belonged to my greatgreat
greatgrandfather
from the early part of the 19th century
and icons that I've picked up around the
world, you know, over the years. I have
a a cross where somebody carved 1820
into the bottom of it, the crucifix. And
so I I've got them all on a on a shelf
and I'm looking at them and St. Nectario
is one and I have holy oil from the
monastery and and holy water and stuff
like that. And I'm looking at the icons
and I said, "Am I really that bad of a
guy that I deserve this? Really?
What is it that you wanted me to do that
I haven't done? Why do I deserve to be
treated like this?"
I remember saying it out loud at 3:00 in
the morning.
And I remember being tempted to start
boycotting church, which I had never
done before. Like, ah, I can't believe
in this stuff anymore. And then I
thought, "No, that's what the devil
wants me to do. I'm going to stick it
out." And I will say, you know, there's
one part of the Greek Orthodox liturgy
where the priest says where the priest
asks God to bless those who love the
beauty of thy house. And I really do
love the beauty of his house. You know,
even after all these years, decades of
sitting in church, I still look around
at the iconography and I just marvel at
it. I marvel at it.
And that got me through.
>> Did you reflect on the passion?
>> My God, my God, why have thou forsaken
me?
>> All the time. Like every time I start
feeling sorry for myself, I think to
myself, you should be ashamed feeling
sorry for yourself. After what all these
other people went through, after what
Christ went through himself, and you
feel sorry for yourself, shame on you.
And it snapped me out of it.
>> Yeah. I don't I can't wrap my mind
around how people in other faiths
grapple with the problem of the mystery
of human suffering.
>> Yes.
>> Because to me, Christianity has the
second person of the trinity
exemplifying how one should bear
suffering.
>> Yeah.
>> And if we didn't have that, how do I
handle my child dying from leukemia, my
wife dying in a car accident?
>> Exactly.
>> How do you even wrap or being betrayed
by someone you love?
>> Yep.
>> Or a friend of mine um who is one of the
greatest heroes I've ever known. and he
saved more lives than anyone, but he's
constantly depressed and feels like a
failure because when you do a job like
his, you fail a lot and you don't
remember your successes, you remember
your failures. And while he was doing
this all over the world, his wife was
running around
um where they were living. And um I
called him and I said, "Brother, I'm
really so sorry." And he said, "It's
very painful, but I'm just grateful that
I can I feel like now I'm really getting
empathy to how our Lord suffered to be
betrayed by people you love."
>> There it is right there.
>> And I thought, "Wow,
>> there it is right there."
>> Pretty powerful. So during those years,
those dark years, did you ever kick
yourself self and say, "Why did I do
this?"
>> No.
>> Never once.
>> I never did. And I can't even really
vocalize to you why I didn't. Well, like
I say, my ex-wife used to say it was
because I'm so arrogant and so
narcissistic that I my brain won't allow
me to think that I did the wrong thing.
I'm like, "Okay,
all right."
And
so, I just accept it. Maybe I am
arrogant. Maybe I am narcissistic. But I
know that I did the right thing. I know
it. You and I were have had this
conversation in the past where the CIA
culture is such that they want you to
believe that everything in life is a
shade of gray. Everything. And that's
just simply not true. Some things are
black and white. They're right or wrong.
And in our guts, we all know what the
right thing to do is. All of us know.
The question then in modern culture is,
is the right thing also the expedient
thing? Right? If you do the wrong thing,
maybe you'll make a little bit more
money, maybe you get that promotion,
maybe something good happens to you in
the short term, but is that how you
really want to live your life?
You know, and that's not how I wanted to
live my life. Another thing, too, is
money has never been important to me.
And I know that doesn't really make
logical sense to a lot of people, but
money was never really important to my
parents.
And because it wasn't important to them,
h I grew up, you know, just as a kind of
a normal middle middle maybe slightly
lower middle uh class existence. I never
saw the ocean till I was 16 years old.
Never went on a plane until I was 18
years old. I we just never
never did those kinds of things. We
never had the money to. And so when I
went into government service, God knows
you don't do it for the money. They're
not paying you anything. when I when I
got hired by the CIA, my annual salary
was $17,200.
You don't do it for the money.
And so I thought, well, you know, this
is my lot in life. This is what I was
meant to do. It's not about making
money. It's just about doing the right
thing. And I came to, you know, really
believe it.
>> And so as you're going through all this,
you never had regret. Now, if I map your
life out and then I'm going to Gen Z,
you are the icon to Gen Z. And there's
no one I would rather be so grateful
that they have found you because there's
a bewildering
>> mix of people they look up to and they
all have like glimmers and flashes of
virtue and then ah but like you you are
a man of that presents himself and Gen Z
recognizes having integrity
>> and they it's just like they drink they
binge watch I I told you the one time my
kids came to meet with me it was the day
that my two old my my 19-year-old and
18-year-old son wanted to tell me they
wanted to work for me for a their like
serving the vulnerable people through
the vulnerable people project and they
said yeah dude there's this guy you'd
love uh John Karaki like this is early
on and they were like I said I don't
know who you're talking about then they
started describing I'm like oh John
Keryaku they go yeah I'm like oh I
turned my phone around look who just I
was texting with my kids like eyeballs
popped out and they said dad do you know
who he is I'm like yeah he's my friend
he goes no no he's the biggest guy in
the world I'm like does he know that I
don't think he knows at and he's like he
has to know it like Gen Z has discovered
him. So, you know, Gen Z to me has been
totally forgotten. The Pope Pope Leo
just came out with this beautiful
encyclical that's being criticized
>> on AI.
>> Well, the the Greek Orthodox Archbishop
of America came out with an encyclical a
couple of days ago saying everybody
needs to read Pope Leo's encyclical
because he's right on.
>> I I thank God for him. You know, it was
a fluke. I was in Rome for the um for
the Conclave and I was wearing a Chicago
White Socks hat. Wow.
>> And so NBC Evening News and Chicago ABC
wanted to interview me and they had
asked me why he took the name Pop Leo
and I said I think it's because he
recognizes that AI is a threat to the
working class the way the industrial
revolution is and we'll probably get an
encyclical drawing on Ram Navarum and
that's exactly what we got and he has
such a thoughtfulness that AI first of
all the apps pornography has brutalized
their moral imagination destroyed their
ability to experience authentic
awakening of the erotic. um they've got
the Only Fans, all of this, and then now
you have AI, so you're never going to
get married, you're never going to have
kids, and guess what? Now you're never
going to have a job. And it seems like
the whole world is out to lunch on this.
>> Um and so Gen Z is just like, does
anyone care about us? Is anyone thinking
about our future?
>> Yeah.
>> And then here you are, and they and they
discover you. Can you explain a little
bit? Why do you think Gen Z has
responded to you so powerfully?
>> Well, the way it started is odd. It's
kind of a disconnect. So, I gave an
interview in January to uh Steven
Barllet at Diary of a CEO, the Diary of
a CEO podcast.
>> So, it was just this January when it
took off.
>> It just happened. And I've been telling
the same stories for 19 years and nobody
paid any attention. So, I gave this
interview and it was kind of the
standard long- form podcast interview,
the same interview I I've given to
Tucker Carlson or or Joe Rogan or a
couple of others. It was a little bit
more philosophical.
And then I, you know, got on the plane
and went home.
A sophomore from the University of Texas
at Austin took that interview and cut it
into shorts,
sped up my voice, slowed down my voice,
shot lasers out of my eye,
and
>> I'm loving this.
>> And it went completely crazy. Right
after that interview, I flew to Dubai. I
had a a contract there and my niece
called me and she said, "Uncle John,
you're exploding on TikTok." I said,
"Why?" And she said, "I don't know, but
it's huge." And I was like, "Oh, okay."
The next night at 2:30 in the morning, I
get a call from the Creative Artist
Agency, the biggest talent agency in the
world. They didn't know it was in Dubai,
so it was like afternoon for them. And
the guy says,"Tell me you're not
represented."
And I said, 'N no, I'm not represented,
but what's going on? And he said, 'You
just blowing up the internet.' And they
wanted to represent me. And I said, but
why is this happening? And they were
like, we don't know, but it's happening.
And I said, okay, sign me up.
That's the origin of it. But the result
has been
that it seems that Gen Z trusts me
because I'm a trutht teller.
I don't have any personal agenda, none.
I think that for the most part,
mainstream media lies to us every single
day. And I think that young people need
to develop the analytic skills necessary
to get to the bottom of issues on their
own because they're not going to get it
from Fox and CNN and MSNBC and the
others. They're not going to get it.
People ask me all the time, where do you
get your information? My answer is from
literally everywhere.
>> Yeah,
>> it takes me hours every morning. And I
start with the Washington Post, the New
York Times, the Wall Street Journal, the
LA Times, the BBC, the Times of London,
AP, Reuters, Al Jazer, Al Monitor. I
just go down this list of 25 different
outlets
because you educate yourself enough from
every single point of view
so that you can make your own conclusion
based on the evidence that you're
seeing.
>> So there's no email I can subscribe it.
No, I haven't found it. And I think that
people have concluded that I'm telling
the truth. The truth has hurt me
significantly over the years. And I just
continue to tell the truth. It really is
as simple as that.
>> Could it be they also feel abused and
abandoned by the establishment?
>> I think that's a survivor who was abused
and
>> you know, look at look at uh
affiliations with political parties.
They're at historic lows right now.
I really believe that we're headed for
some sort of a watershed political event
in the country. Um I'm not exactly sure
what that's going to look like yet, but
think of it this way. As recently as a
century ago, we had as many as six
viable political parties in this
country. We had cabinet members. Think
of Solomon P. Chase, the the Secretary
of the Treasury under Lincoln, or or
William Stanton, Secretary of War under
Lincoln. They were each members of six
different political parties. If you had
a problem with a position that your
party took, you just quit.
>> And Lincoln didn't like any of them, I
think.
>> And team of rivals.
>> Yeah.
>> And you would just jump to a different
party.
So how did we box ourselves into this
you know this essentially uni party this
duopoly that's really a uni party when a
century ago we had we had a populist
party we had a socialist party we had uh
you know the free soil party and this
party and that party and the farmer uh
DFL the Democratic farmer labor party
and we had all these different parties
that were winning seats in Congress that
were winning governorships. Why have we
relegated ourselves to two sides of the
same coin? So, I think we're headed
we're headed towards something big. I'm
just old enough to remember
1968 and 1969.
I remember sitting on my dad's lap. He
was watching the news and the news
showed all these buildings on fire. And
I asked him why these buildings were on
fire and he said, "A very bad man killed
Martin Luther King and black people were
very upset." I still remember him saying
it like that.
And then a couple months later, my
mother just crying all day because
Robert Kennedy had been shot and killed.
And then a friend of ours, a friend of
my parents, um, lost his daughter at
Kent State. She was one of the the five
that was shot and killed. Yeah. So I
remember this upheaval, these riots in
the streets and the
>> this was forming you. This was forming
your moral conscience
>> very much
>> losing a friend losing his daughter at
Kent State must have been a big part of
your identifying with the left.
>> It it very much was Governor Rhodess
Governor Rhodess was the governor of
Ohio that ordered the National Guard
just open fire on unarmed students and
in our house Governor Rhodess was the
devil. you know, open fire on unarmed
students for a peaceful political
protest. What is this? North Korea, you
know, and so yeah, that did inform my my
political views.
Um,
so I don't know how we've gone from
the free thinking of ' 68 and 69 through
74,
which was the year of Watergate,
to this thing where we pretend to have
these significant political differences
and we're just rearranging the deck
chairs on the Titanic.
>> That's that's what's happening. And
Jenzie knows it and they know it.
>> They're like, "We're on the Titanic and
y'all are rearranging the deck chairs."
They recognize it. Yes.
>> And Pope Leo recognizes it. And Pope
Leo,
>> your patriarch recognizes it.
>> Pope Leo has been
has had his intellect consistently
underestimated.
>> Yeah.
>> Mhm.
>> Well, he's from Chicago after. He's a
Socks fan.
>> That's right.
>> So, there's that.
>> And he's been around the block.
>> Yeah.
>> So, I have some questions from Gen Z for
you.
>> Okay. Great.
>> Okay. I had Jenzers. Uh the hope of the
FE, you know, they're they're they're I
they're what gives me hope. Okay.
Is the CIA Oh, no. No. I want to ask
this question first because this is a
good question.
Okay. Not saying that the moon landing
was faked or that the CIA was involved
in the killing of John F. ity. But as
someone who worked inside the
intelligence community, do you think the
US government could keep a secret that
big, faking the moon landing,
assassinating a president, or hiding
aliens from us? Could they, if they
wanted to, hide that those secrets from
us?
I hate to be wishy-washy, but yes and
no.
Um, the the moon landing wasn't faked,
of course. Um, we've got the science to
prove it. But, uh, you know what? I'm
going to answer that with an anecdote
that Bob Kennedy Jr. told me. And when
he told me this, I said, Bob, you've
you've got to write this down. This
social scientists need to know this.
He said that
he said that on November 22nd,
did I say this already? November 22nd,
1963,
>> the day that his uncle was assassinated
in in Dallas, his mother went to the
junior high where he was attending in
Mlan, Virginia, minutes after the
assassination, and pulled him out of
school. And they drove back to the
house, it was called Hickory Hill, big
mansion in Mlan, Virginia. And he said
he got out of the car and his father was
standing in the driveway speaking with
John McCone, who was the director of the
CIA. As background,
both the Kennedys and the Mccons were
very devout Catholics
and
Mrs. McCon had died six months earlier
from breast cancer. The Kennedys were
very worried about Director McCone. They
were worried that he was so distraught
by her death that he might harm himself.
And so John McCon had dinner with the
Kennedys nights a week. And after
dinner, he and Bob Kennedy would go
swimming together.
So Bobby Jr. gets out of the car, walks
past his dad, and he hears his dad say
to Director Mccon, "Tell me your people
didn't do this."
And McCone answered, "I don't know who
did it." He did not say, "Of course my
people didn't do this." What in the
world would make you think the CIA would
kill the president of the United States?
That's not what he said. He said, "I
don't know who did this." So, did the
CIA kill John Kennedy? Of course not.
Did elements of the CIA kill John
Kennedy?
I think that's something that we'll
never know the answer to, but I think
the circumstantial evidence is such that
we should be asking these questions
because it's entirely possible.
>> So, you know, as an outsider, when I
hear there are rogue elements within the
CIA, I'm saying to myself, "Oh, please
let that just be Hollywood fantasy." No,
there there are rogue elements
especially, you know,
pre-1975, pre-Curchp Pike committees,
immediately post 911.
Yeah, I kind of make a joke about this
uh this guy that I used to work with,
friendliest guy in the world, Rick.
I was working in the counterterrorism
center and he would come in every day.
Morning fellas. We say morning Rick.
How's your weekend fellas? Hey, great
Rick. How was your weekend? Yeah, great.
Hey guys, you going to go to the agency
picnic? Yeah, Rick, we'll see you at the
picnic. Finally, I said to the guy I was
sitting next to, Frank, I said, you
know, he's the nicest guy in the world,
and I really don't know what he does
here. And Frank says, he's the head of
the special activities division.
So, his job was every Tuesday morning,
you get the kill list, which is what
they called it. Every Tuesday morning at
the White House, CIA people meet with
the White House council and their
people, come up with a list of people to
kill that week. Rick gets the list. He
sends his guys out. He goes out all
around the world. You kill the guy
that's on the list and you come back and
you get the next list the next Tuesday.
And I said, "Wow, that's that's not
good, right? I mean, none of these
people have been charged with a crime.
If these are such bad people, I mean,
this is the United States of America.
Yeah,
>> we have a constitution.
>> If these guys are so bad, charge them
with a crime. You can't just decide you
don't like somebody's politics and go
and blow their brains out. And as it
turned out, some of them were American
citizens
who had never been charged with a crime.
Again, some things are right or wrong,
and this is wrong.
After I left the CIA,
Rick retired. He I left in ' 04. He
retired in like ' 06. And in ' 07,
Vanity Fair magazine wrote an expose
about him. I couldn't believe what I
read.
He had been a hitman for the Cali cartel
and he struck up a friendship with
a dark figure
in my career who ended up becoming the
deputy director for operations
because they were both working against
communist insurgents in Colombia
because the Cali cartel hated the
communists and vice versa. Well, the CIA
hated the communists and the enemy of of
my enemy is my friend. And so the agency
and the Cali cartel are working together
to stamp out communism. As if that
mattered.
And so he says, "Hey, listen. Uh, if you
don't want to do cartel hits anymore,
I'm I'm the CIA station chief down here.
Why don't you come and do hits for me?"
And that was it. He was a hitman for the
Cali cartel. That's not That's not cool.
>> No. No. How did that happen?
>> Are we still doing this?
>> Are they still getting the kill lists?
>> Uh, we don't know. They won't they won't
say. They won't tell us. The kill list
was outed in um the Atlantic Monthly
magazine. The um originator of the kill
list was one John Brennan. And uh we
don't know if
>> John Brennan's drone war killed hundreds
and hundreds and hundreds of children.
>> Oh my god. I have a friend Daniel Hail.
Daniel just got out of prison himself.
He was a drone operator from the US Air
Force. He's the one who blew the whistle
on the drone program and he tells the
most chilling story.
He was operating a drone from a base in
Nevada.
His boss was at McDill Air Force Base in
Florida. So, they're both looking at the
screen. Daniel's operating the drone and
he sees the target. The target's in
Afghanistan, right?
And Daniel says, "I have eyes on the
target." And his boss in McDill says,
"Fire."
And Daniel says, "Wait a minute. He's
with two little kids."
And his boss says, "Those aren't kids.
Those are goats."
He said, "I'm looking at them. They're
not goats. They're children. They're
girls." And his boss says, "Fire."
And he said, "I can't fire. They're
children.
>> It's an illegal order." He says, "Fire
or be court marshaled."
And he fires.
And he kills a 12-year-old girl and a
nine-year-old girl. And he went home
that night and he said to his
girlfriend, "I became a child killer
today."
How do you how do we live with
ourselves?
>> How do you recover from that?
>> You can't recover from that.
But this is what I what I mean when I
say
>> in Israel right now, they have a ramp.
The suicide rate of IDF soldiers is
unprecedented.
>> It's got to be because you can't all be
monsters, right?
>> Yeah.
>> Somebody's got to have a conscience.
>> Not Lindsey Graham.
>> No,
>> not Randy. Fine.
>> Lindsey Graham is perfectly happy to
kill your children and your children and
your children. He doesn't care. Yeah.
And fine. Who wears an IDF uniform onto
the floor of the house like a traitor.
>> Who did? Oh, fine. All right. Yeah,
Congressman. Fine. He was shown a
picture of a dead Palestinian child.
>> Yeah.
>> And he said, "Oh, that's a lovely
picture. I'd like to see more of those.
That this isn't an international
scandal." But then Jen Z is watching
this
>> and they're utterly horrified.
>> Talk like that.
>> Yeah. That's not how normal people talk.
Ben Gavir, you listen to Ben Gavir talk?
>> His wife, listen, the Israelis passed a
law two weeks ago allowing for the death
penalty, but only for Palestinians, not
for Jews. And on the day that the
Knesset passed it into law, his wife
baked him a cake in the shape of a
gallows.
These are not normal people. This is not
normal life. We need to reclaim what's
right. You know, I think we're going to
see a political shift in this country
like we did after desegregation.
And ironically, it's going to be around
segregation.
>> You know, when you look at Israel, it is
a segregated apartheid state. It makes
the Jim Crow South look like utopia.
>> Very much so. And I think it's hard for
most Americans to believe that, but you
have settlers attacking Christian
villages with the IDF pulling security.
So if you try to protect yourself,
protect your property, you're shot right
in the face or arrested.
>> Yep. And how many American citizens have
been killed in the West Bank?
>> One was kidnapped this week.
>> And does the American government lift a
finger?
>> No.
>> To do anything in the name of justice?
Nothing. Literally nothing.
>> It's frustrating. I could talk to you
about the West Bank and Gaza and
Lebanon. I mean, that's the nightmare,
too. Okay, so here's some more Gen Z
questions.
Um,
what do you know about Project Gateway
and using astral projection to spy on
the Soviets during the Cold War? This is
the men who stare at goats question. Is
that what this is? Okay,
>> so Project Gateways was a part of what
was called MK Ultra. MK Ultra was a very
very
broad scope operation that began in 1952
and ended in 1975. It included a lot of
different things. ESP, astral
projection, mind readading,
um LSD and using LSD
to get people to
confess to their deepest, darkest
secrets. A whole bunch of different
stuff. It was a disaster and it ended up
in the deaths of a lot of people, a lot
of innocent people. So, the way it
started off was
the CIA recruited a source who was a
fake, a phony source who said, "Hey, the
Russians are experimenting with this,
you know, ESP and astral projection and
mind reading and all this stuff. We're
behind the eight-ball." That wasn't
true. The Russians were not doing any
such thing. the Chinese were, but we
didn't know that. So, we said, "Oh my
god, we have to we have to get up to
speed as fast as we can." The CIA comes
up with this program, MK Ultra, and they
start just pouring resources into it,
beginning with LSD.
And because the CIA
often moves into the area of utter
lawlessness,
they start dosing their own employees
unwittingly.
You just just slip LSD into people's
coffee and, you know, their food and
just just see what happens to him. Well,
I wonder what's going to happen to Joe
if I dose him with LSD.
>> Jacob's ladder if you movie.
>> Well, Joe's going to go to the roof and
jump off because he thinks he can fly.
And then you got to explain to his kids
why your dad went to work this morning
perfectly normal and then committed
suicide at lunchtime.
>> And this that happened.
>> Yeah, that happened. In fact, um there's
even been um a documentary about it. So
that was one part of it. They hired
psychics and seers and readers and and
it was all silliness and nonsense. It
never amounted to anything. But then
there were sub operations of MK Ultra
like MK Chicwit for example
uh where we broke into the lab in
Switzerland and stole the formula for
LSD so we could make it better
and then we just decided to
I'm not making this up. It's all it's
all out there on online. You can find
it. We decided to make San Francisco the
sort of the the headquarters of these
experiments. And so
>> so hippie culture, the grateful dead
fish,
>> all this all at the same time
>> is the fruit. Yes.
>> Of CIA.
>> It all came out of the CIA. So we
decided to recruit a whole contingent of
uh prostitutes
and we set up a safe house. So, we sent
the prostitutes out to pick up John's
clients,
dose them with LSD, bring them back to
the safe house, tie them down, and get
them to confess their deepest, darkest
secrets. And it just didn't work. They
were just, you know, jabbering
incoherently and having flashbacks and
freakouts and it just didn't work. And
then we decided,
well, let's uh
let's come up with a germ
and we'll wait until a really foggy day
when the air is really heavy and we'll
just shoot this germ into the air in San
Francisco and just see if anybody gets
sick
because then we can do it in Moscow and
really screw them up, right? So, we come
up with this germ that's developed in a
CIA lab. We wait until an unusually
foggy day and then just drive around the
city with these big pipes just blowing
the germ into the into the atmosphere.
Two days later, 11 people came down with
this extraordinarily rare upper
respiratory infection that had never
been seen in San Francisco before. And
we were like, "Hey, that worked.
We should we should do that in the
Moscow subway system and see if we can
really, you know, screw them up."
Then there was another experiment where
they um they decided to dose. There's a
small village in France. I forgive me.
>> How many people knew about this? Was
this a small
>> At the time? It was very very small. It
was tightly held. Um it was a
compartmented program.
So we we went to this village in France.
It had one bakery that supplied the
entire village and we dosed the yeast in
the middle of the night. We broke into
the bakery and put LSD in the yeast. The
baker comes to work in the morning. He
makes all the bread. He sells the bread
to everybody in the village. Everybody
in the village goes on an LSD trip. And
then for decades, we were like, "It
wasn't us. It wasn't us. It wasn't us."
And then in the '9s, we're like, "Okay,
it was us."
And then finally in 1975,
the CIA had just gone too far, right? We
we've just lost the Vietnam War, and
everybody in the CIA is like smuggling
heroin back from Vietnam. and it's just
a disaster. So, Senator Frank Church, a
Democrat of Idaho,
convenes a a special committee known as
the Church Committee. Sen uh Congressman
Otis Pike, a Democrat from Long Island,
convenes a a parallel committee in the
House side, the Pike Committee. They
morphed into the Senate Select Committee
on Intelligence and the House Permanent
Select Committee on Intelligence and
they started investigating the CIA, what
what was then called the family jewels,
where they demanded literally everything
that the CIA had. Well, the first thing
that comes up is MK Ultra and Associated
Assassination Programs. The CIA wasn't
supposed to be assassinating people. In
fact, it was out there assassinating
thousands of people.
So, Congress put the brakes on that.
Senator Church specifically told the CIA
director, "Do not destroy the MK Ultra
documents."
Direct order. He literally went from
Capitol Hill back to headquarters and
said, "Destroy everything."
And so, everybody in the building is
just shredding documents.
They destroyed 85% of the MK Ultra
documents. 15% survived. That's why we
have this little idea after all these
years of what it was. But we really
don't know what the overall program was
because it was all destroyed. Well, the
director was fined $500
for this egregious criminal act of
defying Congress. And the old-timers
used to talk about this when I first the
IDF does for soldiers when they
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah. By God, you're going to
be fined $500. What happened was he was
held in contempt of of Congress. He was
found guilty, fined $500. He went back
to headquarters and the old-timers told
me that every CIA employee had lined the
halls and they were throwing dollars and
$5 into a hat to pay the director's $500
fine
just as a big FU to to Congress.
>> What caused it that? Was it the the
shock of World War II and you still had
this culture that were facing
existential threat from social
communism?
>> That's exactly what it was. It was the
communist boogeyman.
Well, um, also in 196 I'm sorry, in
1975,
Senator Church and Congressman Pike
insisted on an executive order that
became known as EO12333.
Executive Order 12333 became the basis
for what the CIA was allowed to do
overseas and not allowed to do. And the
original draft, the original version,
signed version of 1233 forbade
assassinations.
Okay. Until September 12th, 2001.
And then President Bush kind of crossed
that part out and said, "Kill anybody
you want."
And that's what they've been doing ever
since.
>> Now, are these assassinations done by
the special activities group? Are they
like in the movies? Do they poison
people, have heart attacks, commit
suicide, or is it just
>> all different?
>> So, it's as sophisticated as in the
movies?
>> Yeah, it is. It can be. I mean,
sometimes it's as crude as, you know,
the guy's walking his dog. This happened
recently. I read in the paper. Uh, the
guy's walking his dog, a van pulls up
alongside, the side door opens, you get
a bullet in your brain, the door closes,
and the van drives off.
>> That's when they're sending a message.
They want people to know what happened.
>> Sometimes they'll kidnap a guy and then
nobody ever sees him again. There there
were times when I was the executive
assistant to the CIA's deputy director
for operations.
After I got back from Pakistan, I got
promoted and the the deputy director
made me his assistant. In that position,
you see literally everything that the
CIA is doing everywhere in the world.
Compartments six levels above top
secret. It was ridiculous. I couldn't
even sleep at night. But
you you see
I have to be careful with what I say
here. you see some some things that
you're like, "What?
Why would we do that, right? We're
either a nation of laws or we're not a
nation of laws. You can't pretend to be
one while being the other. If you don't
like this guy's politics, you can't just
walk up to him and put a bullet in his
head." You know, we we would get these
cables like, "Oh, uh, we were uh
interrogating this guy uh during the
night and um Jim may have gone a little
too far, but um
well, he's deceased now, so what should
we do?"
And then the the geographic uh office
will write back, "Well, where are you?"
"Well, we're next to the safe house. can
you just bury him in the backyard?
Yeah, we'll just do that. And they just
dig a hole and bury the guy. And then
years later, you see these newspaper
articles like so and so's family, they
haven't heard from him in years. He he
was there one day and gone the next and
like where could he possibly be? I I can
tell you where he is.
He's buried in the backyard of the safe
house.
That's not a nation of laws. That's not
what a nation of laws does. So, we're
either going to be the good guys or
we're not going to be the good guys. But
we can't pretend to be one while being
the other.
>> And if we're not the good guys, we won't
be able to remain our position as the
sole hedgeimon.
>> Exactly.
>> Your competitor
>> because the rest of the world is wise to
us and it's all going to collapse around
us.
>> They're wise to us now.
>> Yeah.
>> How do we What would your advice be to I
you look at what's happening in Lebanon
right now. It's scandalous. It's
shocking. It's unimaginable.
And uh it's just as if things are just,
you know, I I have a different view of
the German people in the 30s and 40s.
Like what could they have known?
>> We have phones bombarding us with
information every day. The Germans would
not have known what was happening in
Awitz or in the Eastern Front or in
Paris. Um but the American people have
access to this information, but they
have rational ignorance. So I have to
pick my kids up from school. I have to
My boss wants this report. My wife wants
me to make more money. they're just
thinking about their life and they don't
have time to think about the decimation
of ancient Christian cities,
monasteries, churches, schools. Um,
well, if you were to sit down across
from President Trump and say, "This is
what you need to do so we can reclaim
and maintain our position in the world,"
what would you say?
>> I think that he needs to put the
interests of the United States first
above all else. We have secunded our
foreign policy to Israel and Israel
security is not my concern as an
American. My concern is the security of
the United States of America and joining
ourselves at the hip with Israel is
dragging us down. You know, there was a
you know the Onion
I love the Onion, too. They had a
headline a couple weeks ago that just
really hit
>> and it said um
>> China content to sit back and watch US
destroy itself.
Exactly.
Because that's what's happening. We're
destroying ourselves. Listen, when when
you have votes in the United Nations
General Assembly every single year for
the last 50 years, and literally the
entire world is on one side and on the
other side is the US, Israel, Costa
Rica, and Nau.
There's a problem.
We're not smarter than everybody else in
the rest of the world every year
joining ourselves with the Israelis.
>> And it's undermining our interest in the
world.
>> It is. It's really undermining the
world. You know, when I went to Israel
last time, 2022, one thing I saw that at
first perplexed me and then just pissed
me off
>> when you're in the old city in Jerusalem
and you're approaching the Western Wall,
right? There's like a museum there and
and some think tank or whatever. People
had put up these signs like glued these
signs to the walls and they said America
we are with you. It's like what? First
of all about what? Secondly,
>> you're the size of Milwaukee.
>> Yeah.
>> We don't want you with us.
>> What are you with us on? Yeah.
>> Yeah. It it hurts us that you're with
us. We don't want you. You can't live
with civilized countries.
>> You just hit the nail on that though. I
think the average like boomer me who
would have been me even though I'm a Gen
Xer to the Gen Z, anyone over anyone who
didn't have a smartphone in their pocket
during puberty is a boomer. And I think
that's a good designation because it's
true. They're different than the rest of
us.
>> That's right. Yeah.
>> And so as a typical boomer conservative
Republican, I would have if I would have
heard that 15 years ago before I had a
lot of experience in the region, I would
say, "What are you talking about?
They're the only civilized country in
the region." And I had this I had this
idea that they were democracy.
>> I had this idea that they were
surrounded by all of these just
barbarians. And then you go to Lebanon
and Jordan and Iraq and Syria and and
Palestine and like these are beautiful
deep and in the Middle East they're even
very proud. They're like we're not like
the Gulf States. We have a culture and a
civilization. They do.
>> And they do.
>> They do.
>> Yeah. They do. Like you have the Yazidi
that are the protometic people that have
been living in the same valleys since
Abraham left Abraham left years. Yes.
>> Christian communities praying in
Aramaic.
>> Yes.
>> Where St. Thomas put a church.
>> Yes. Exactly.
>> And then you're going to watch the 700
Club or John Hegy and you're going to
preach theology to first century
Christian communities in the Holy Land
that's ancestors were in the upper room.
>> Yeah, that's exactly right.
>> So what would you say to the boomer
Republican who's been watching 700 Club
since the 90s, watching Pastor Hegy,
watching Fox News? They just can't hear
it. Read the history. You've got to open
your mind to the history. Don't believe
some guy yapping at you on your TV. You
have to read and understand the history.
It really is as simple as that. But
people do what's expedient. It's it
takes time and it's hard and maybe it's
boring and but you've got read the early
church fathers. Just go there. Go
through the West Bank. Take a drive.
>> That's a great idea.
>> From Bethlehem to Tybee.
>> That's a great idea. changed
>> forever.
>> I couldn't agree more.
>> This is the last Gen Z question, which I
really love. What beliefs did you hold
strongly at 30 that you no longer
believe today?
>> Oh, that's
>> And by the way, you're an Angry Birds
legend. This is from Colin.
>> I live.
>> You're an Angry Birds legend.
>> For Angry Birds,
>> by the way, that's something my kids
loved about you. Like, dad, like he just
talks about his love for Angry Birds.
It's like, who does that? That is so
cool. But it's that kind of transparency
and honesty that you were like reflect I
needed to do I need to play. This is
what makes me happy. This is what I do.
>> It brings me joy in the morning.
>> It brings you joy.
>> Yeah.
>> I love it.
>> I I have a routine in the morning. This
is apppropo of nothing but I have a
routine in the morning. I play Angry
Birds that takes about an hour 50
minutes. I play the daily uh solitaire
just because I have a streak that I
don't want to break. But my doctor told
me to do the New York Times crossword
puzzle every day because it actually
does fend off, you know,
the degeneration of the brain and I
don't want like I don't have dementia in
my family on either side, but just to be
on the safe side. I want to keep my
brain fresh. So I do the Washington Post
crossword, the New York Times crossword,
the uh USA Today crossword if I have the
time, Angry Birds and what's the most
challenging of the crossword?
>> The New York Times. Okay. Yeah,
especially Saturday. Okay.
>> Saturday is way harder than Sunday.
>> The pros.
>> Oh, yeah. Saturday's tough. Like I I'm
twothirds done with today's. It's hard.
>> But anyway, um what do I not believe now
that I believed at 30? That we are just
unequivocally the good guys. It's just
not true. It's not. I also believed I
used to say all the time, I want my
leaders to be smarter than I am, right?
to make wise decisions.
And I've I've come to realize they're
just human beings. And most of them
aren't smarter than the rest of us.
They're just more political and, you
know, found themselves in positions of
power.
Um
>> they have the same nervous system, the
same bandwidth, the same
>> Yeah, I'll tell Yeah, they do. I'll tell
you a story. When I was when I was in
college, um I I was very fortunate to
win this thing called the Lynden B.
Johnson congressional uh scholarship or
internship. So, it was the only paid
internship on Capitol Hill. And I worked
for my congressman. He was a
conservative Democrat from Western
Pennsylvania, pro-life, proun, pro
labor, you know, the old old school
Democrat. And um I like the guy a lot. I
sat next to the press secretary who was
this really, really good-looking. She
had been Miss Iowa of all things, and
she was dating an Exxon lobbyist. He was
a great guy, too. See, he'd come and
hang out in the office all the time. One
day, the congressman comes in.
I'm only saying this because he died
recently, so he can't like sue me or
anything, but the congressman comes in
one day and he goes like this. He goes,
"I got laid last night."
And I said, "No, he didn't. Mrs.
Coulter's not even in Washington. She's
in Pittsburgh." And I was like,
and the lobbyist said to me, "You see,
they're all dogs. They all put their
pants on one leg at a time just like you
do, and they're all dogs who think that
they're better than everybody else." He
said, "I don't know why you idolize
these guys." And he was right.
He was right.
I went into I went in to see um the
assistant secretary of state one time.
he had he called me and asked me to come
over to uh he wanted a briefing on this
really like obscure issue dealing with
the Gulf. So I went in and um he said,
"You know, I was at the White House the
other day in this mutual colleagueu's
office and I saw a picture on his desk
with that friend of yours." I said,
"What friend of mine?" "That woman you
sit next to." I said, "What are you
talking about?" He said, "The director
has a picture of himself with the woman
you sit next to." I said, 'They're
they're both married. And I was like,
"Oh, for heaven's sake."
>> And they don't even it's not even And
next thing you know, they both get
divorced. They marry each other. It's
like, you know, it's Payton Place over
here. We used to have this joke at the
CIA
that when you go into a conference, a
conference room, never touch the table
because you don't know who was having
sex on it last night.
And it was serious. In 2004, 2003,
um, we had to send doctors from the
Office of Medical Services out to Iraq
because CIA officers were passing around
a CIA specific strain of gorrhea amongst
each other.
>> It was seen only in CIA officers. And
the doctors are like, "Can't you people
control yourself?" Brett Mcgherk got
caught on the top of the embassy having
sex.
>> Yes, he did.
>> This and that guy is an animal. I'd love
to do a documentary expose on him.
>> You and I should chat about that
afterwards. I got some stuff to tell.
>> I mean, that guy and and when I would
when I was in Iraq documenting the
genocide,
>> the Peshmerga and I'd meet with senior
leadership and I'd meet generals. I do
too. But they'd all have US embassy
stories.
>> Yeah. Because they're all pigs.
>> They're pigs. They talk about they'd
have to get a shuttle because they were
so drunk they couldn't even So, this is
where I would have empathy for them.
Um, I have to imagine if they're engaged
in high-risisk adultery in front of
everyone at the office.
>> Let me tell you,
>> that they have existential angst.
They're lonely. They're desparing and
they just want to that this is kind of
tragic. So, it's a culture of tragically
lonely people, which then if I was a
foreign,
>> if I was another intelligence agency, no
one's easier for me to recruit than
someone who's lonely and alienated.
>> And they're all lonely and alienated.
Alienated. Let me tell you, my deputy
director that I worked for had been
married five times and all five of his
wives had first been his secretary.
All five of them. I'll give you another
example. When I was working in Pakistan,
um I was dating a senior CI officer who
became my wife. So, we were just dating
at the time. I had just gotten divorced
and um we had this uh trunk line in the
in the station. So even though I was in
Pakistan, I could pick up that phone and
it was a local Washington DC number. So
we were 11 and a half hours ahead. So
when I'd get to the office at 7, I would
call her at 7:30 the previous evening in
Washington and we would just talk about
how our day was. So one of the guys in
my office, I had seven old-timers
um working for me. They had all been
either director or deputy director of
near east operations and they came back
after 9/11 just for patriotic reasons.
But if you're a contractor, you can't
lead a group. So I was the chief of the
group and all of these senior
intelligence service officers were
working for me, which was a great
blessing for me. I learned more from
them than I learned over the rest of the
course of my career.
>> And these were men that came up in the
when it was all on the line.
>> The Yeah. the bad old days. So,
my girlfriend and I would end each
conversation with, "Okay, love you.
Mwah." And hang up. And one of them
heard me and he says, "So, are there
wedding bells in the future?" And I
said, "Oh, I don't know. I I just got
divorced. I'm kind of afraid of being a
two-time loser." That's what I said.
Two-time loser. He says, "Two-time
loser? I've been married four times."
Dave, how many times have you been
married? He says, "Five for me. Bill,
how many times have you been married? I
got three. Frank, how many times have
you been married? Four for me, he says.
Two-time loser. Kid, you're just getting
started. He says to me. And I said, "Oh
my god, I don't want to be like you
guys."
I get home,
we get married,
and one night we're sitting on the floor
of the living room watching a movie.
It's like midnight. We're watching this
movie and her cell phone rings and it
happened to be next to me. I picked it
up and I said, "It's like a 16digit
number." I said to her, "I think it's a
satphone." And she says, "Answer it. See
who it is." So I said, "Hello." And this
voice says, "Is Heather there?" And I
said, "Tony."
And he said, "Yeah, who's this?" I said,
"It's John. Where are you?" He said,
"I'm in Afghanistan."
And he said, he said, 'Why are you
answering Heather's phone?' I said, '
Uh, because she's my wife. Why are you
calling Heather's phone at midnight? Oh.
He goes, I'm sorry. I didn't realize
that you two were together. I said,
Tony, why don't you use your one minute
of sat time every week to call your own
wife instead of calling mine?
But that's typical of the CIA. They
don't care. And that's a problem in the
culture that should be seen as a real
security problem.
>> I worked for these two guys. I loved and
respected both of them, Mike and Jean.
Two of the finest officers I ever worked
for. And they hated each other. So one
day I said to Jean, I said, "Jean, you
and Mike are both you're two of my
favorite people. I don't understand why
you hate each other so much." And Jean
says, "I'll tell you." He said, 'Our
together, we were in Karach and Mike
screwed my wife. I said, 'Oh my god,
that's terrible. I'm so sorry to hear
that. And he said, 'N no, that's okay.
He said, um, our second tour was Bogotaa
and I screwed his wife.
>> And I said, you know, this is exactly
what's wrong with this organization. He
said, shame on both of you.
>> By the way, am I naive? I just think if
I'm wanting to recruit somebody, I want
to recruit someone who's just betrayed
by someone in his own organization in
such a horrible way.
>> Exactly. Right. Talk about a
vulnerability.
>> That seems like quite a vulnerability.
Then you have a culture like this where
Brent McGurt's on the top of the
embassy. The whole Middle East knows.
>> Yeah. The whole Middle East
>> and he's in charge of the war against
ISIS. This seems kind of a
>> You're exactly right.
>> It seems like a problem that needs to be
fixed.
>> Amen.
>> I mean, I could talk to you forever. I
don't know how much time we have, but
that's the next question. What how do we
fix the culture of CIA to serve the
interest of the American people? Can it
be fixed or does it have to be shattered
and swept away? The only way it can be
fixed is with true robust congressional
oversight, which we have not seen since
1982.
>> Can we see it when we know the ethics of
guys that have to go elected every two
years?
>> No, I don't think so. I mean, Mark
Warner, Tom Cotton, come on. These guys,
>> Randy Fine.
>> Randy Fine, please. What a joke. It's
all a big joke. I I've I've said in
podcasts in the past, there was one guy
on uh on the Senate Intelligence
Committee that I kind of expected a
little help from. And when I got out of
prison, I was invited to dinner at the
Greek ambassador's residence. So, I go
and the senator's there, member of the
intelligence committee, and he comes up
to me and he says, he says, "Hey,
welcome home. Congratulations. We were
really worried about you." And I said,
"Oh, come on, senator." I said, "I
expected more from you. you of all
people. I expected a little bit of
support. And he goes, "Look, it took
everything I had just to not lose my
security clearance." And I said, "Oh,
you're afraid of them."
Now it makes sense to me. And we've
never spoken again.
>> He's he was never a free man.
>> No, never. He's afraid of them.
>> And one of my favorite stanzas and lines
in any poem is in Rudier Kipling's if.
And I was just talking to my son about
this and actually talking about you. It
is if when all if all men can count on
you but none too much, you're a man. And
I said to my son, do you know what that
do you understand what that means? He
says, yeah, that you're just that you
put justice and truth over friendship
and loyalty. I said, yes. I said, let me
ask you a question. If anyone if one
person in this world can count on you
too much, then can anyone count on you
at all?
>> There it is. And that's the reality.
>> I want to ask a hypothetical question,
okay, of the folks that are here. This
is something that I like to raise at uh
at colleges and universities because
it's kind of indicative of what every
CIA officer has to deal with, especially
if you're a field officer, you're out
doing operations. So,
let's say that you're a CIA case officer
in the Middle East and you've recruited
a bonafide terrorist, a bonafide
penetration of al-Qaeda, Hezbala, ISIS,
whatever it is, it doesn't matter. You
meet with this person once a month in a
hotel somewhere in the Middle East and
this person has given you actionable
intelligence that you've used to disrupt
attacks and save American lives, right?
He's the real deal. So you go out to
Aman or Cairo to do a meeting and he
says to you, "I've been good to you and
I've given you everything that you've
wanted. So tonight you're going to do
something for me. I'm not giving you any
more information until you go out and
get me a prostitute. So, I always ask,
do you get him the prostitute? Show of
hands. Right. Seriously, show would you
get him the prostitute?
Yeah. The answer is yeah. It's nasty and
dirty, but this is the job that we've
chosen. You get him the prostitute.
What if he asks you for a child
prostitute?
Well, obviously the answer is absolutely
not. Not under any circumstances. But
that's not even the issue. The issue is
there are no rules. There's no training
class to say, "Well, you know, you can
get him the prostitute, but you can't
get him the child prostitute because
there's this line. Nobody's going to
teach you that." So you have to go into
this job into this life with your own
set of moral principles and you have to
stick with it because there's not going
to be anybody at the other side at the
other end of the cable at headquarters
saying h you probably shouldn't do that
or rule number 125A says yes to the
prostitute but no to the child
prostitute. It's all up to you.
And so, you know, so many guys and
women, mostly guys, lose the sense of
who they are once they get into this
position. And once it's lost, you can't
reclaim it.
I thank you for that. Okay. I want to
end on a kind of a happy note. You are
record setting a cameo right now.
>> I know it's crazy, right? So cameos
where you it's a service where you can
get a famous person to give someone a
birthday wish or something like this
>> and you are like setting cameo records.
>> Broken all the cameo records.
>> You've broken all the cameo records.
>> And um when we first were talking about
having you on my film, you're like I
love a line in your film. So and I'm
like yeah of course I love you in my
film for your sad card. Dude, you don't
need that anymore. You've well blown
past that.
>> Got the sad card.
>> So you you how many hours a week are you
leaving messages?
>> Just answering cameo requests. I'm doing
probably
25 or 30 hours a week.
>> So that's how many cameos a week?
>> I did 900 for the month of March.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. So what we want I want to know is
of all these cameos,
what was the sweetest one?
>> Uh I've gotten three. I've I've done
about
1950 cameos so far.
>> Okay.
>> I do 20 or 30 a day.
I've gotten three where well let me let
me back up about 50% of them are
birthday wishes you know uh Jimbo's
birthday is next Tuesday I say hey happy
birthday Jimbo John Kuryaku here hope
you had a great day you know etc
so there's birthday you know mother's
day father's day whatever
advice
pep talk about 10% are pep talks so of
the 10% that have been pep talks
Three have come back to say that I
somehow talked them out of committing
suicide.
I'm not really sure how I did that. But,
you know, there are a lot of really
hurting people out there. We get so
wrapped up in our own lives, our own
existences, we don't realize how many
other people are in pain. There's one
girl, she's just one out of almost 2,000
cameos that I've done. one who sounded
like she was in such pain. I said,
"Listen." In the cameo, I said, "We're
not supposed to do this, but here's my
phone number."
>> Wow.
>> Call me. And she called me crying. She's
15. She's bimic.
Her parents don't understand her. She
was going to commit suicide.
And I talked her out of it. And um she's
called me twice since then, usually for
less than a minute or two. very
respectful,
>> very very respectful. And she said she
just she's having a down day and she
needs to hear a friendly voice and
that's it. I had another friend
friend um he became a friend. So
I get it I get an a message through
Facebook. The guy says, "Hi, my name is
James and I want to thank you for what
you did for the country."
So, I look at his page and here's
picture after picture after picture of
him embedded with the Syrian Kurds
fighting ISIS.
And I was like, "Wow." I said, "Thank
you. Thank you for what you did." I
said, "The Kurds are heroic. I've loved
the Kurds all of my adult life since I
first, you know, started working with
the Iraqi Kurds in northern Iraq."
And we became friends. This guy had the
most tragic story.
His mother was a prostitute and he was
born with fetal alcohol syndrome.
So
never had any idea who his father was.
And when he was 17, he he did something
really really stupid. He kidnapped a guy
at gunpoint and took him from ATM to
ATM, forcing him to empty his bank
account. And of course, he got caught
and the judge came down on him like a
ton of bricks and gave him 20 years. And
he did the whole 20. Well, he gets out.
He's 37 years old. He's got a violent
felony on his record. Employment is
impossible.
So, he goes into porn. It's the only
thing he can do. He acts in porn. And
what do you make in porn? I don't know,
$150. Who knows? So he decides he he
needs meaning in his life. So he goes to
Turkey, crosses the border into Syria,
stumbles into these Kurds, takes up
arms, and just starts killing ISIS
people. He does that for a year, and
then comes back out, makes his way back
to the United States, Billings, Montana.
So,
we start talking and he can't find a job
and I'm a convicted felon and I have
this this uh violent felony and I don't
have any education and he didn't have
anything going for him. And I kept
telling him one day at a time, go to the
local community college. What's a
community college class cost? $100,
$150, whatever you're interested in, you
know, whatever, whatever, you know,
tickles your fancy, focus on that. Just
one day at a time, I'm telling him. Then
one day, I get a call on my phone and it
says prison/jail
and it has some Wyoming
Wyoming area code. I'm like, what in the
world? So, I answer the phone and it's
him. I said, "What in the world are you
doing in jail in Wyoming?" He said, "I
got into a fight with my girlfriend and
she wouldn't let me see my son and I
slapped her and she had me arrested." I
said, "Geez, James." So, he ends up
getting bail
and then decides he's going to commit
suicide. So, he goes back home in
Billings, Montana, takes a gun from his
mother, drives to the Walmart parking
lot. He's sitting in the car holding the
gun getting ready to kill himself when
an offduty ATF agent pulls into the
space next to him to do his grocery
shopping,
sees this guy with a gun, pulls his gun,
and disarms James.
So I get a call, Billings, Montana
County Jail. I was like, you've got to
be kidding me. So I answer. I said,
"James, you're in jail in Billings,
Montana now." He says, he's crying. I
was gonna kill myself. I was in the
parking lot at the Walmart. I said, "Oh
my god." He said, "I need a I need an
attorney." I said, "All right." Because
I'm a sucker for a Saab story. I always
have been. So, I start calling every
attorney in Billings, Montana, and I
find one that's willing to do it, you
know, for a price.
So he gets him out, but felon with a gun
is a mandatory minimum of five years.
The the courts are or the prosecutors
asking for eight years because he had a
violent felony and this is bad.
Then he calls me one day, July 4th,
2022,
and he said, "Hey, uh, my sister, uh,
lit an M80 and it blew three of her
fingers off, and she was in surgery all
day, 14 hours. They reattached her
fingers." I said, "Oh my god, that's
terrible, James. I'm so sorry. Tell her
I send my best. I'll send her a card."
And I said, "But you sound you sound
good." He said, "Yeah, I feel good. I
feel good. Things are going well." I
said, "Great. Okay. Good to talk to
you." Two days later, his sister calls
me. I said, "How are your fingers?" She
said, "Oh, they're okay. It was my own
stupid fault, but they reattached them.
I'll recover." And she said, "But that's
not why I'm calling. I'm calling to tell
you James killed himself last night."
I said, "Oh my god, what happened?" And
she said, "Um,
he told their mother he was going for a
walk. He walked to the neighbor's house
or yard. They had a big oak tree and he
strung up a noose and he hung himself
and he left a note and all it said was,
"Please call John and tell him I said I
was sorry."
And you know, it reminded me of a story.
Have any of you heard of the folk singer
Pete Seager?
Pete was a giant in my life next to my
father and my grandfather. No man had as
much of an impact on my life as Pete
Seager did.
And he told me a story one time. There
was another folk singer from the 70s,
Phil Oaks. Um, Phil was as popular as
anybody in the 60s and early 70s, but he
went on a concert tour in Africa and he
was mugged in Africa and the mugger cut
his throat and he recovered, but he was
unable to hit high notes after that and
he fell into a deep depression.
And Pete told me that that he Pete was
performing at a folk club in Granch
Village one night and the gig ran late
and he was packing up as quickly as he
could because he had to literally run to
Grand Central Station and catch the last
train to Beacon which is where his home
was. And as he's packing up, one of the
waitress says, "Pete Phil Oaks is on the
phone for you." And he said, "Tell Phil
I can't talk. I have to run and get the
last train to Beacon." And so he said,
"Tell him I'll call him tomorrow." And
he left. And Phil Oaks committed
suicide.
And he said to me, and this was unlike
anything I had ever heard Pete say, he
said, "That selfish bastard. I'll never
forgive him for what he did. He had no
idea how many people he's hurt." And
that always stuck in my mind.
>> Could have saved your life
>> and your dark days.
>> Very well. May.
>> Did you ever think about that when you
were considering suicide? 100%.
>> So, he saved your life
>> and you saved a 15-year-old girl's life.
>> There it is.
>> So, when you were going through all the
rough things that you went through and
your brother told you this is the best
thing that ever happened in your life,
he didn't realize it was the best thing
that was going to happen in a lot of
people's lives.
>> Yeah, it's true. We're all here for a
reason. And it just keeps reminding me
that there's always somebody who's
suffering more than I am.
And the privilege of suffering is you'll
be able to use that empathy to help
someone else another time. You lose your
child to a drunk driver. There's going
to come a day where you're helping
someone who lost their childhood.
There's that's the empathy is the gift
of suffering.
>> That's right.
>> And so it's interesting that we must
have a suffering nation because they've
really identified with you. You've
really done the whole arc of the hero's
journey. Your, you know, your call to
adventure was not when you thought. It
wasn't when you joined CIA. No,
>> it's when you the moment your adventure
began was the moment you said
>> and who would have thought who could
have foreseen that. I never could have.
>> Yeah.
>> I had never believed you if you had told
me listen in the next 10 years this is
what's going to happen.
>> I think when we first met if I would
have told you that. Well, you didn't
believe me. Jenny and I were like look
we're passing on your movie because we
are this is a massive studio film. This
is the perfect script. It it you wrote
it in your life.
>> Yeah.
>> Like you literally hit each of the
points of the mono myth in your life.
>> Crazy.
>> And then you were discovered
by young people,
>> which is the greatest reward. It really
is.
>> You know, when you were you were walking
down the street to a book reading and I
had called you and um when I was asking
you to do this, I think I like this is
kind of an unbelievable opportunity. I
don't know if you can do this. And I
thought there was no way you could fit
in your schedule. And you're like,
"Yeah, yeah, yeah." But as you're
walking to the book reading, someone you
could hear how excited they were to see
you, but then you seemed more excited to
see Thank him. And you said, "If not for
you, I could be living out of my car. If
not for Gen Z, in a way, you would have
a whole fight ahead of you."
>> Yeah.
>> A whole life of battles.
>> It's true. It's true. Yeah. The CIA did
its darnest to make sure I could never
work again.
>> WW didn't work.
>> Yeah. Didn't work.
>> Didn't work.
>> I mean, here's how bad things got. And
I'm not saying that this is bad. I mean,
maybe in the greater scheme of things,
it's bad. But I was so broke and so
unemployable. I had to I had to rent a
house with two elderly gay guys who were
attached to oxygen machines, walking
around like smoking cigarettes with
their oxygen. And I'm like,
>> so this is my lot in life.
>> What were you watching? Wheel of
Fortune. What did they watch?
>> I know, right?
>> I don't know.
>> Jeopardy at 7:00 and Wheel of Fortune at
7:30. I'm sitting there like this.
>> Yeah. Like, well, I guess this is the
way it's going to be.
>> And then everything exploded.
>> But that's what heroism looks like. It's
not uh, you know, it's not the Rambo
stuff. It's the long drawn out years and
years of not thinking it's going to get
better.
>> Was there a point where you just said,
"I'm I'm good. It's going to be like
this forever and I can handle it.
>> Yeah, it was a conversation I had with
my sister. I said, you know, I don't
mind being poor. I've actually become
accustomed to being poor. And um I said,
the only thing is I don't want to die
alone and I especially don't want to be
sick for a whole long time before dying
alone. My sister's five years younger
than I am and she's very, very kind and
empathetic. She's my best friend,
really. And she said, "Don't be
ridiculous. you're going to you're going
to live in my house. She said, "The
whole the whole basement? It's this
beautiful apartment. They have a an
enormous house in uh Bedford, New
Hampshire." And I said, "Great.
I get to live in my sister's basement
for my remaining days."
Thanks, Tina.
>> You know, my organization runs a shelter
in Warz, Mexico.
>> Even better,
>> for migrant worker for migrant unwed uh
migrant unaccompanied women with
children. So we have a shelter there and
the shelter director said if I have in
my old days if I have nowhere to go
they'll let me go to the shelter in
Warez. You can come to the shelter in
Warz with me.
>> No. Okay. So I want to end on this and
then we'll go to questions and then
we'll decide with the audience. I don't
know if they want to be in the in the
video or not but
>> um I want to pay a cameo. How much does
a cameo cost? I want to buy a cameo
right now.
>> Hey, thank you. You know the algorithm
changes the price every 15 minutes based
on how u how much
>> I'll pay you cash so we don't have to
share with the website. No, we'll kick
it to you. No. So, this is my cameo,
right? I want to do it right now. Okay,
here's my cameo. To Gen Z, I want you to
give them a cameo pep talk to a
generation that they want to be creative
writers. They want to be filmmakers.
They want to be lawyers and they're
looking at AI and that's gone. They want
to have marriage and love and family,
but that seems impossible. So, I want
you to give Jenz your cameo pep talk.
>> Yeah. Okay. Gen Z, John Kiryaku here.
Listen, I know how hard life is right
now. You're seeing changes coming
quicker than we've ever seen really
since the since the advent of the
industrial age. And that's not
necessarily a good thing. So what you
have to do is grab life by the horns and
live it according to your standards.
Don't let AI put you out of business.
Don't let internet porn take away a
chance at a at a beautiful relationship
or marriage. You have to grab life by
the horns and live it according to your
own rules. So do what makes you happy.
do what allows you to contribute to
society and you're going to live a happy
life. All the best.
>> That was awesome. John, I want to thank
you. you know, um,